Guide to the Elizabethan Club, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Elizabethan Club, Yale University, records
1900-2013
RU 36
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9.75
The records consist of minutes of meetings, financial papers, correspondence, membership lists, sketches, video recordings of the Maynard Mack lecture series, and portraits of the Elizabethan Club at Yale. Included are records of the club librarian, the club chairman, and the chair of incorporators.
Elizabethan Club (Yale University)
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 40 (YRG 40), Records of Yale clubs, societies and organizations.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records were a gift of the Elizabethan Club, 1978, 1980, 1999, 2007, 2013-2014.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the materials is restricted. Written permission from the Librarian of the Elizabethan Club is required.
Arrangement
The records are arranged alphabetically by type of material, followed by new accessions.
Biographical / Historical
The Elizabethan Club was founded in 1911 when Alexander Cochran donated the clubhouse and Elizabethan collections to Yale University. The club provides a setting for students and faculty to share tea while discussing literature.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of minutes of meetings, financial papers, correspondence, membership lists, sketches, video recordings of the Maynard Mack lecture series, and portraits of the Elizabethan Club at Yale. Included are records of the club librarian, the club chairman, and the chair of incorporators.
College students -- Societies, etc.; College teachers -- Societies, etc.; Literature -- Societies, etc.; Elizabethan Club (Yale University); Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Societies, etc.; Yale University -- Students
- Records, Series I
  - Admissions Committee
    - Candidates for admission, 1912-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - General material regarding club admissions, 1929-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2-9)
    - Honorary members, 1923-ca. 1940 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Membership lists, incuding necrology, 1946-1964 (Box 1, Folder 11-14)
    - Minutes books, 3 volumes, 1912-ca. 1949 (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
  - Annual meeting
    - General material, including related correspondence (many years missing), 1945-1984 (Box 1, Folder 18-35)
    - Minutes, 1911-1963 (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
  - Board of Governors
    - Admission of women to membership, correspondence and straw vote material, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Constitution and articles of association, 1911-1951 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Incorporators, includes correspondence, deed of conveyance for 123 College St., printed ephemera, minutes, and other club management documents, 1911-1987 (Box 1, Folder 40-45)
    - Lists of board members, includes membership on various committees, 1912-1941 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Meeting material, includes related correspondence, and after 1930, various committee reports submitted to the Annual Meeting
      - 1912-1928 (Box 1, Folder 47-63)
      - 1928-1989 (Box 2, Folder 64-111)
    - Special meeting, 1955 October 22 (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - Correspondence
    - General
      - 1911-1950 (Box 2, Folder 113-136)
      - 1951-1965 (Box 3, Folder 137-153)
    - Bartlett, Henrietta, Greg correspondence, 1916-1934 (Box 3, Folder 154-155)
      General
      See also: Publications, Shakespeare census, box 5, folders 236-238
    - Cochran, Alexander Smith, correspondence and typescripts of newspaper articles, 1911-ca. 1940 (Box 3, Folder 156-158)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 10, Folder 248)
  - Elizabethan Club house (459 College Street)
    - Alarm system, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 159)
    - Renovation, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 160-162)
  - Ephemera and artifacts
    - Burghley, Lord, manuscript fragment, correspondence, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 163)
    - Lounsbury, Thomas, photograph, Circa 1900-1915 (Box 3, Folder 164)
    - Osborn, Bob, sketch of Shakespeare on wood panel and accompanying note, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 241)
    - Prothalamion (1596), title page, 7x5 inch negative, Undated (Box 3, Folder 165)
    - Shakespeare Society of Philadelphia memorials, 1930-1955 (Box 3, Folder 166)
    - Signet Society, seventieth anniversary printed ephemera, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 242)
    - Sizer, Theodore, correspondence and photograph detailing a panel showing Queen Elizabeth I's coat of arms, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 167)
    - X-radiographs of the club's portrait of Queen Elizabeth I before restoration, Circa 1980s (Box 10, Folder 250)
  - Events
    - Anniversary, 75th, fundraising material, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 168)
    - Annual dinner, correspondence and printed ephemera, 1989-1993 (Box 3, Folder 169)
    - Bé, Kenneth, lute recital co-sponsored by Elizabethan Club at the Beinecke Library, Yale University, compact disc (CD-R), 2003 November 5 (Box 7)
    - Club Night, Stephen Parks talk, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 170)
    - Exhibit in Sterling Memorial Library to commemorate the accession of Queen Elizabeth I, exhibit labels, 1984 January (Box 3, Folder 171)
    - Glorious Feast
      - Newspaper clippings, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 248)
      - Planning materials, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 172-173)
    - Maynard Mack Lecture, posters, Circa 1980s (Box 10, Folder 249)
    - Schubart Memorial dedication, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 174)
  - Financial records
    - Contributions, Circa 1970-1979 (Box 3, Folder 175)
    - Correspondence and membership lists relating to club's financial predicament, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 176)
    - Endowment, 1939-1965 (Box 3, Folder 177)
    - Founders fund, Circa 1930-1940 (Box 4, Folder 189)
  - Library
    - Correspondence
      - Keogh, Andrew, 1911-1925 (Box 4, Folder 190-194)
      - Troxell, Gilbert, 1931-1965 (Box 4, Folder 197-199)
    - General, includes invoices and correspondence, 1980-1997 (Box 4, Folder 201-217)
    - Giroux, Robert, research project on "The Book Known as Q", 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 218)
    - Librarian's reports, 1920-1978 (Box 5, Folder 219-220)
    - Librarian's reports relating to gifts, 1967-1979 (Box 5, Folder 221)
    - Lists and inventories
      - Books in original gift, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 222)
      - Books on deposit at Yale University Library, 1916-1925 (Box 5, Folder 223)
      - Books, pre-1700, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 224)
      - Paintings and prints, includes correspondence, 1932-1962 (Box 5, Folder 225)
    - Logan Project, bibliographic notes and correspondence, includes Eugene Waith files, 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 226-227)
  - Newspaper issue and clippings, general, 1968-1989 (Box 10, Folder 248)
  - Notecards containing notes from Andrew Keogh's office, and information about club members, Circa 1915-1935 (Box 8)
  - Notecards containing notes from Andrew Keogh's office, and information about club members, Circa 1915-1935 (Box 9)
  - Officer files
    - President, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 228)
    - Vice-President, 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 229)
  - Publications
    - Anniversaries
      - Thirtieth, correspondence and printed ephemera, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 230)
      - Fiftieth, reminiscences and printed ephemera, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 231)
        - Newspaper clippings, 1958-1961 (Box 10, Folder 248)
    - Annual letters, Circa 1955-1970 (Box 5, Folder 232)
    - Elizabethan Club catalogue, correspondence, proofs, and research material, 1982-1985 (Box 5, Folder 234)
    - Printed ephemera, 1920-1986 (Box 6, Folder 245)
    - Publications Committee, photograph, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 235)
    - Shakespeare Census, correspondence and printed ephemera, 1912-1937 (Box 5, Folder 236-238)
    - Troxell, Gilbert, The Elizabethan Club: Its Origins and Its Books, publication and notes, Circa 1952-1972 (Box 5, Folder 239)
    - Yale Shakespeare, correspondence and printed ephemera, 1916-1927 (Box 5, Folder 240)
  - Register of guests, 2 volumes, 1970-1980 (Box 6, Folder 246-247)
- Records, Accession 2008-A-007; 0.5; (1 box) (Box 1)
- Maynard Mack lectures and news footage of the Elizabethan Club [videorecordings], 1986-2007; Accession 2008-A-008
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - "Positively Connecticut," Yale Elizabethan Club, Action News (WTNH-TV), commercially produced videotape (VHS), 1986 December 29 (Box 1)
  - Arthur Miller in conversation with Murray Biggs, 1998 November 18; videotape (Hi-8) (Box 2)
    - Use copy, videotape (VHS) (Box 2U)
  - Claire Bloom in conversation with Murray Biggs, 1999 April 18; videotape (Hi-8) (Box 3)
    - Use copy, videotape (VHS) (Box 3U)
  - Edward Albee in conversation with Murray Biggs, 2000 November 2; videotape (DVCAM) (Box 4)
  - Brustein, Robert, 2006 April 19; 2008-a-0008-0002; 1; computer files (DVD-Video) (Box 7)
    General note
    Contact Public Services (phone: 203 432-1735, e-mail: mssa.reference@yale.edu) for information on accessing this digital object.
- Records of Elias Clark, Chair of Incorporators, 1986-1998; Accession 2014-A-044
  - Beecher Hogan legacy, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Incorporators minutes, 1990-1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, misc, 1993-1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Wheelchair accessibility, 1993-1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Entertainment committee and annual dinner, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Admissions committee, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - House committee, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Gilder, Pittman, Shakespeare bust and garden benches, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Notes to members, misc, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Renovation records, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - New ventures-outreach, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Additional material, 1918-2013; 1980-2013; Accession 2015-A-021
  - Acquisitions, 2003-2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Budget, 2008-2012 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Catalogue-new editions, correspondence and ephemera, 1985-2005 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Centenary Committee, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Constitution, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and memoranda, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - History-Goffart article, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - History-Letters from grads, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - House Committee, 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Incorporators
    - 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1991-1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 2005-2007 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Meeting minutes, 1993-2012 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Library
    - Library Committee-general files, 1918, 1993-1998 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 2006-2007 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Gifts, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Reports, 1967-2013 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Outreach Committee, 2000-2013 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of the vault, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Publications, 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Repair and building engineering reports, 2003-2007 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Staff, 2010-2012 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Worsdale portrait, 1990-2005 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Poster listing deceased World War I servicemen from the Elizabethan Club, 1917-1918; Accession 2015-A-059
  - Poster listing deceased World War I servicemen from the Elizabethan Club, 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 1)